<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>holonomic sequences | George Kenison</title>
    <link>https://georgekenison.github.io/tag/holonomic-sequences/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://georgekenison.github.io/tag/holonomic-sequences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>holonomic sequences</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://georgekenison.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>holonomic sequences</title>
      <link>https://georgekenison.github.io/tag/holonomic-sequences/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On minimality and positivity for second-order holonomic sequences</title>
      <link>https://georgekenison.github.io/post/mfcstalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://georgekenison.github.io/post/mfcstalk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Slides from my talk on minimality and positivity for second-order holonomic sequences.  Presentations given at MFCS 2021 (Tallinn), Joint Forsyte (TU Wien) and Institute of Science &amp;amp; Technology Seminar, and Open University Dynamical Systems Seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An infinite sequence $&amp;lt;u_n&amp;gt;$ of real numbers is holonomic if it  satisfies a linear recurrence relation with polynomial coefficients.  Such a sequence is positive if each $u_n \geq 0$, and minimal if, given  any other linearly independent sequence $&amp;lt;v_n&amp;gt;$ satisfying the same  recurrence relation, the ratio $u_n/v_n$ converges to $0$ as $n$ tends to  infinity.
In recent work, the speaker and collaborators establish a  Turing reduction of the problem of deciding positivity of second-order  holonomic sequences to that of deciding minimality of such sequences.  More specifically, we give a procedure for determining positivity of  second-order holonomic sequences that terminates in all but an  exceptional number of cases, and we show that in these exceptional cases positivity can be determined using an oracle for deciding minimality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Inequality Decision Problems for Low-Order Holonomic Sequences</title>
      <link>https://georgekenison.github.io/publication/kenison-2020-positivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://georgekenison.github.io/publication/kenison-2020-positivity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holonomic techniques, periods, and decision problems</title>
      <link>https://georgekenison.github.io/post/holonomictalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://georgekenison.github.io/post/holonomictalk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Joël Ouaknine gave an invited talk on holonomic techniques, periods, and decision problems at Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer Science conference (FSTTCS 2020). During his talk Joël presented some of our ongoing work on inequality decision problems for low-order holonomic sequences (&lt;a href=&#34;https://georgekenison.github.io/publication/kenison-2020-positivity/&#34;&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;).  The abstract and recording  for the talk are given below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holonomic techniques have deep roots going back to Wallis, Euler, and Gauss, and have evolved in modern times as an important subfield of computer algebra, thanks in large part to the work of Zeilberger and others over the past three decades. In this talk, I will give an overview of the area, and in particular will present a select survey of known and original results on decision problems for holonomic sequences and functions. I will also discuss some surprising connections to the theory of periods and exponential periods, which are classical objects of study in algebraic geometry and number theory; in particular, I will relate the decidability of certain decision problems for holonomic sequences to deep conjectures about periods and exponential periods, notably those due to Kontsevich and Zagier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/01j0OtQRjNk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
